Okay, so now that we have our UI sorted out, we're ready to dive into our functionality.
So I'm going to provide a link in the course to this page within my GitHub repository for
this project, and you'll see that I have a words.json file, and you'll see that I have
about 300 words here, none of them are repeating, and these are the words that I used
for my project, but if you want, you can generate your own words.
You could even use an API call to a random word generator, but just for the sake of simplicity,
I've decided to provide you with a words array just to make things nice and easy.
So again, if you go to this link, you can actually click over here and click copy raw file,
and we're going to close this and go back to our code.
In our script, JS, we're going to start by creating a constant words, and it's going
to be equal to, and then we're going to paste in our array of strings.
Okay, and we're going to go ahead and hover over here next to our one, and we're going
to click on this arrow, and we're going to minimize that.
We don't need to worry about our words anymore.
Okay, so now that we have our words, the next step is we're going to want to shuffle
these words.
We don't always want to have the words in order, because then eventually you would get
really good at just typing those exact words, we want to be able to shuffle the words
in our array.
So we're going to go to the next line here, and we're going to comment out a title shuffle,
the words array, and we're going to create a function called shuffle array, and it's
going to take an array, and this is going to use a Fisher Yates algorithm.
I will explain more once we get to the end of the code, but basically we're going to
use a four loop, we're going to loop through the array, and we're going to switch positions
of items in the array, and then we're going to return the array.
But I'll explain more once we're done, so four, let i, which is our index equals array.length
minus one, so because it's zero index, this is how we get to the last item in our array.
semicolon i once it gets down to zero, once our index becomes zero, or while our index
is not zero, I should say, we want to decrement, so i minus minus, we want to go down,
and make our index a smaller number.
So if our array length hypothetically was 100, we'd be starting at 99, and we'd be looping
through until we hit zero, and we'd be going down by one each time, okay, and then we're
going to create a constant j, and this is going to be equal to math floor, okay, and it's
going to return the greatest integer of a whole number, we don't want to round two decimals
here, we want a whole number for our index, and inside of this we're going to use math
random, which returns a number between zero and one, and we're going to multiply that
by another bracket i plus one, so that means that it'll always, at least, be one, and
then below this, our array item at the current index, so square brackets, array, square
brackets i, comma, sorry inside that, array, square bracket j equals, and then we're going
to swap these, so array, square bracket j, comma, array, square bracket i, okay, and then
we're going to return, whoops, outside of the loop, then we're going to return our array,
just to summarize one more time, we are starting at the last item in our array, and we're
incrementing down, so again, if we're 100 as our length, we're going from 99 until our
index is zero, we're going down by one each time, and we're using math random, which
is like 0.13567 times our index plus one, so it'll always, at least be one, and they're
using math for to make that into a whole number, and then we have our array item at the index,
and then we have a random number that is less than our index, and then we are swapping
these two with the opposite of themselves in order to swap the two elements, so we are
essentially shuffling our array in the most straightforward way that we can, okay, so if
I were to now call this, so let's call our shuffle array, and we're going to pass in words,
and we are going to console log this, we want to see what's going to happen, okay, and
let's go back to our browser, and we'll inspect, and let's go ahead and move this, and
then we'll take off, smart phone, okay, anyway let's space, great, so in our console we
have 253 items, so not quite 300, but you'll see that it's starting with twin kingdom
melt urge, so you can see we have shuffled everything, if you look at what we are actually
starting with, it's actually going A, B, C, D, so abandoned beacon candy dove, you can
see that we have shuffled this, and if we go ahead and refresh the page, you'll see that
we've shuffled it again, so now it's starting with leaf or bolt, and now it's starting
with juice and bird grip, okay, cool, so we're effectively shuffling our array, okay, so we
want to combine this array of words into one long string, and then we want to pass that
string into our text container, okay, so let's jump back to the code, and we can remove
this, it'll come into the title, combine shuffled words into one long string with spaces,
we also want to add spaces, so we're going to create a function generate one text bracket,
and then we're going to have a constant of shuffled words, and it's going to be equal
to shuffle array, and we're actually going to use a spread operator to make another version
of the words array so that the original words array stays intact, and then we're going
to return shuffled words dot join bracket, and then single quotes space, so that is
going to add a space in between all of our words, and then we'll go ahead and say let's
long text, we're using a let because this can be changed, generate long text, and then
we'll go ahead and console log our long text, okay, so let's go ahead and check that out,
okay, so you can see we have one long string here, it's no longer an array, okay, awesome,
now the next thing we need to do is actually pass it into our text container element,
so we're going to do this by adding in constants for our elements here, so constant text
container, capital C there, equals document dot get element by ID, bracket single quote
text dash container, and we'll do the same thing for our timer elements, we're at it,
and our try again button, and lastly our final score element, okay, and then we're
going to instead of console logging, we'll say text container dot text content is going
to be equal to long text, okay, so let's go ahead and check that out, all right, nice,
we have our text inside of our text container, great, okay, so that is it for shuffling
our words and pass it into our text container, in the next one we are going to start looking
at the functionality of actually checking what we are typing and seeing if we're typing
the correct character or not, all right, I'll see you in that one, bye for now.